OK, let's get started.
We're already at lecture 20.
That's a bit scary.
I know how how we came all the way to lecture 20.
You know, the semester is almost ending then I think we have 5 or 6 more lectures after this.
I don't know because there's some holidays, I think.
So it may be five, I'm not sure.
But the remaining lectures will be dedicated to memory, which is the bottleneck in existing system.
So it's going to be exciting to learn about how we design memories.
But in this lecture and previous lectures, we already talked about memories, memory banking, for
example.
I'll remind you of some of those things.
So today we'll talk about it.
Yet another exciting topic, which is GPU architectures.
We're going to build on the SIMD processors lecture that we had last week that Muhammad delivered,
where we talked about array and vector processors and GPU architectures are going to be essentially
more flexible.
Array and vector processors.
That's it.
Especially they're flexible in terms of their programming model, which also helps flexibility in the
hardware with some features that enable movement of threads.
More flexible.
OK, let's get started.
I'm going to cover some basics that you have seen already just to jog your memory because last week
we had only 1 lecture.
There seem to be a lot of holidays this this semester.
I don't know, we, we keep having these single Singleton lectures as opposed to having two lectures
in a row.
OK, but we're talking about graphics processing units.
Today we covered SIMD processing.
I'm going to mention some of those things so that you will see how GPU is built on top of that.
And remember we're we're talking about not just micro architecture here, we're talking about
hardware software interface.
Also we had a different programming model for SIMD.
If you remember, these are some of the readings and we're talking about exploiting data parallelism,
specifically regular data parallelism.
And you remember the paper we covered where we categorised architectures into four different things,
single instruction, single data, single instruction, multiple data, multiple instruction stream,
single data, of which systolic arrays are an example, and multiple instruction, multiple data.
In some of the things that we will see today, we're going to combine some of these paradigms
actually.
And GPUs do that in a nice way.
Some other machine learning accelerators also do in a nice way.
And you've seen this picture before where you talked about array and vector processors.
And these are basically doing essentially they, they're exploiting the space-time duality.
I would say in an array processor, the same instructions executed at the same time, but different
instructions are executed or operations are executed in different space, meaning different
functional units.
Whereas in a vector processor, oh, sorry, different instructions are executed in the same space,
basically.
Whereas in a vector processor you execute different operations at a given particular time.
If you look at this point over here, you execute different operations, but you're executing the same
operation, the same space.
Meaning functional units can be specialised to the operations wherein whereas an array processor,
functional units are much more general purpose.
In that sense, array processor is a little bit more expensive potentially.
So existing GP US are going to exploit both of these.
If you remember last week, we talked about this is a purest distinction.
Existing SIMD processors do both array processing and vector processing.
They exploit parallelism in both space and time and GPUs are going to be essentially the same.
OK.
We also talked about memory banking, which we will get to especially starting tomorrow.
Banking was needed so that you can actually have multiple accesses serviced concurrently across
different banks so that you can tolerate the latency of a single access.
And if you, if you remember in the Cray processor, the memory access latency was 11 cycles and they
needed to have 16 banks Oregon more than 11 banks or at least 11 banks so that they can get one
word out of memory per cycle, right.
So banking is a concept that we will get back to and it's really necessary so that we can get high
throughput from memories.
And we're going to talk about high throughput memories, especially with GPUs today because we have
so much compute parallelism because of array and vector processing.
So we will need bigger and bigger memories and higher and higher throughput memories.
So banking is going to be very important.
OK.
We also talked about bank conflicts.
I'm not going to get into that again, but this is a this is an issue that plagues a lot of
programmers who want to get high performance from their systems.
How do you ensure that two accesses don't conflict in the same bank?
If you can actually parallelise all your accesses to go to different banks in memory, you can get
the data at high throughput.
But if you actually have a conflict in a bank, then your data will be delayed as a result.
What your processor would be stalling, right?
And we talked about how to do this, but I'm not going to get again talk about it because this is
last week's material.
I'll just mention this beautiful paper from 35 years ago from Bob Rau, who actually invented
partially the VLIW architectures.
I mentioned that in the VLIW lecture, and they had the same problem in the VLIW processors because
you exploit a lot of parallelism.
And if the data accesses loads and stores go to the same bank, you have conflicts and you have low
throughput and your pipeline stalls.
Because in the LIW, remember that the principle was to make sure that you don't have any complicated
structures in the pipeline, right?
And you have lock step execution as a result, if one instruction stalls, all of the instructions
after that stall.
So if you're interested, there's a lot of interesting math in this area as well.
And existing GPU is actually employee a lot of the techniques that are developed in this paper and
also other papers that came after it.
Because again, memory is important.
You need high bandwidth access to memory.
Even if you have thousands of banks, still you get bank conflicts.
And you don't want bank conflicts.
Ideally, you won't like to eliminate all bank conflicts.
OK, so I already mentioned this.
Most modern SIMD processors are a combination of both array and vector processors.
They exploit data processing, both time and space.
And we're going to delve into GPUs, but just to jog your memory, we've given you this example in the
last lecture.
You can see that there's a vector instruction over here, which is adding vectors A&B and storing the
results in vector C So every element is being operated on using one single functional unit over
here.
As you can see, this is vector processing you, and this is a combination of both array processing
and vector processing.
If you look at this, four elements of the vector are being operated in parallel across four
different functional units, but then the next four are operated in a pipeline manner in the same
functional unit.
So you're exploiting parallelism in both space and time.
Over here.
We'll see this again in GPUs.
We're going to rename things in GPUs because GPUs are going to make things more flexible.
They're not going to have vector instructions, they're going to have regular scalar instructions,
but they're going to be part of different threads.
And essentially we'll do the same thing with a slightly different context.
OK, And if you remember, this is also, this was also shown last time.
I'm still jogging your memory.
We had partition vector registers so that different elements of an array can be accessed only for
from different only from particular functional units.
Basically, you partition the register file across the functional units.
If you have an instruction that needs to operate on element 0, it has to go to this lane.
For example, GPS will have the same issue.
Basically, if you have a thread that needs to operate on a particular register, it has to be mapped
to a particular lane because the register files partitioned, different registers are partitioned
across these lanes.
So we'll get back to this picture again, and we said that you can overlap the execution of multiple
vector instructions.
This was an example again.
I'm going to get to this example again later with, for example, a 32 vector length and a machine
width of eight load execution units.
You can do 8 loads per cycle and you finish the vector in 4 cycles.
And you can see that you unleash a lot of parallelism with a single instruction and then multiply
maybe operating on the results coming from the load unit, and then add, maybe operating on the
results coming from the multiply unit.
And basically you can fill the pipeline with these vector instructions very, very quickly.
And you can see that there's a lot of computation happening in the GPUs.
The computation will be actually millions and millions of operations, and memory will be
increasingly strained.
If you get millions of loads at the same time, you're going to be in big trouble basically.
OK.
We also talked about automatic code vectorisation and it's going to be important because I'm going
to build on this to introduce how GPS operate.
We said that this is a perfectly vectorisable loop, meaning there are no dependencies across loop
iterations.
So you can easily write a scalar sequential code for this, and if your compiler is smart, it can
basically identify that there are no dependencies across different iterations.
It can vectorise the code automatically.
This is in general very difficult to do because compiler analysis to ensure that dependencies don't
exist across across different iterations is not easy in many cases.
For example, if you had an I -1 over there, compiler would not be able to do what I show over here.
But here it's obvious that they're independent.
So the compiler basically puts together the iterations side by side, pictorially at least, and forms
a vector instruction, vector load over here that operates on different iterations, right, Different
data elements, in other words, right, because each iteration operates on the next data element that
comes.
And we said that you.
Vectorisation is essentially A compile time reordering of operation sequencing, right?
As opposed to sequencing the operations in a sequential manner like this, you sequence the
operations in a different way, in a parallel manner with vector instructions.
OK, not easy to do, but there are some applications like graphics where this is actually nicely
doable.
Because imagine a huge image, millions of pixels, and you're doing the same operation to every
pixel.
That's a lot of parallelism, right?
That's essentially this loop.
That's why graphics is a very good example of an application that fits single instruction, multiple
data.
Of course, depends on what you do with graphics, but in general, there's a lot of parallelism in
graphics processing, OK?
That's why GPUs have been the most successful SIMD engines of the world.
OK, we also discussed this.
Essentially, vector or SIMD machines are good at exploiting regular data parallelism.
Same operation performed on many data elements, improved performance, simplified design, no
intervector dependencies.
This is going to be true of GPUs also.
Performance improvement is limited by the vectorisability of code.
That's going to be true of GPUs also.
This is exactly why the Cray machine, Cray first Cray machine was a heterogeneous machine.
They did not have the most powerful SIMD unit of its time.
They also had the most powerful scalar unit of its time because Cray recognised that M das law was
so important.
If you cannot vectorise your code completely, you'll be bottlenecked by the serial bottleneck that
we have discussed also.
And essentially, if you don't have a good serial execution engine, your vector processor is not high
performance.
That's been the cornerstone of designing super computing systems and that's going to be affecting
GPU also.
That's why existing GPU architectures try to execute scalar code very well also.
So they add for example, sometimes CPU like units inside, sometimes they do heterogeneous computing
CPUs and GPUs together, especially in consumer grade devices.
And going forward, this is going to become more and more important.
OK, We also said that many existing ISA include ISA include CMD operations and that's where we
stopped.
But before that, I will show this picture again.
This is actually a very nice picture of M Das Law and the serial bottleneck.
Basically, serial bottleneck is where you have only one thread over here and this cannot be
paralysed.
And if that is a reasonable fraction of your code, then you're in trouble.
Even if you throw infinite number of parallel processing elements, you're not going to be able to
speed up that code, right?
That's the idea.
So GPUs will suffer from the serial bottleneck as well.
So keep that in mind.
OK, let me cover these very quickly because I don't intend to cover what Mohammed covered, but this
is to show you that SIMD operations have been quite successful even as specialised accelerators for
single instructions.
Single data IS as right.
X86 ISA, for example, is a sequential von Neumann ISA, but it has components that are SIMD
essentially, and they're added as instructions like all good von Neumann architectures do.
You sequence through these instructions also, and we've seen the SIMD extensions that started with
the MMX operations in 1990s and over time, and we've seen examples of how you can compare things in
parallel.
And this, this was an example of matrix vector multiply.
This is a paper from 1990 introducing Intel MMX operations.
Here we are in 2026.
Everybody's talking about matrix vector multiplication for some other reason, not for graphics,
right?
It's good to think about it, right?
Applications change, but some fundamental operations remain.
And I think this is good to also think about because there are many ways of accelerating matrix
matrix or matrix vector multiplication.
This is one way as part of your sequential ISA, right?
And you've seen this example last time.
I'm not going to go over, but I will tell you a story.
This was very controversial at Intel in 1990s when Uri Weiser who invented and developed along with
Alex Pelig the MMX technology that they called it, was met with let's say fierce opposition with an
Intel saying that no workloads uses.
Why are we investing in an accelerator that would accelerate the SIMD operations multimedia.
This is always a chicken and the egg problem, right?
No workloads use instructions because instructions doesn't exist, of course, right.
But if you put the instruction, you're making a bet and the bet is hopefully some workloads will use
it so that they can gain speed UPS.
And they did this bet, they made this bet and I think they won't in the end.
So this was a very good design decision in the end for Intel to change the instructions that
architecture because it's been, it's actually enabled CP US as an accelerator for graphics and many
operations for many, many years.
And in my opinion, they also delayed the, let's say successful success of the GP US a little bit
because you could actually.
To these operations as CPU with a specialised unit.
So you can see that as an architect you need to make decisions and you don't know the future, right?
Maybe nobody will use the instructions and extensions that you provide.
Because it is true that those instructions and extensions are not very general, right?
They do very specific things with small width elements.
It's not like a huge vector processor, but they've proven extremely useful, OK?
And you can see that these extensions have increased over time.
Intel added the streaming SMDAVX, which is actually much wider extensions, 512 bits as opposed to 64
bit operations.
And more recently, because of again, matrix vector multiplication or matrix multiplication, they
added the matrix multiplication units they called AMX.
Essentially, these are specialised units to do matrix multiplication.
We can think of it, and some of these are actually very, very high throughput.
You can look at the Wikipedia page or the Intel manuals to see their throughput.
OK, But they're all built on the SIMD paradigm.
OK, So Mohammed gave a lecture.
There's another lecture.
If you're interested in SIMD, there's more online.
Before going into GPUs, let me talk a little bit about the prevalence of SIMD, because it's not only
in GPUs.
There are also other accelerators that people use today that use SIMD, the wafer scale engine that
we discussed for example, by Cerebrus.
Remember there's a chip this big, and this is the more recent version.
You can see that there's a lot of memory, there's a lot of processing at the same time.
This is actually a combination of paradigms.
Basically, they want to the, the main reason they designed this processor was to accelerate machine
learning.
Again, initially training, but they figured out, I think training is not that easy.
So if they're pushing inference more on this one, but I think it could, anything that could be used
for training can potentially be used for inference, clearly.
But basically they want to map a neural network, a large neural network to the wafer and the wafer
is partitioned into many dots.
So to control this machine, they actually have a multiple instruction, multiple data model.
Essentially it's a multi threaded machine overall.
That's how you program it, where you have distributed memory, which we will talk about later on.
But if you look at this, these are the multiple dyes.
They have 84 dyes and you have 4500 tiles in one version of this processor.
And each tile is an independent execution unit and they communicate with each other through routers.
So you can think of this as a distributed system that's on a wafer, right?
And clearly you need to program it somehow, you need to compile into it.
But it's not just MIMD, there's also internally inside each processor to accelerate machine learning
operations.
They have SIMD processors very similar to what you have seen.
These are smaller SIMD processors.
They essentially they have, they can do for operations, each operating on 16 bit floating point data
types.
But imagine having 4500 of these.
So there's actually a lot of parallelism that you exploit if you can exploit it.
So there's local SRAM also.
OK.
If you're interested, the CTO of Cerebas had given a invited lecture in this course some number of
years ago, so you can go and watch it if you're interested.
I should also say that SIMD operations are not limited to, again, CPUGPUS or other accelerators, but
Fpgas have been used by Microsoft in this particular case to accelerate again neural networks.
And if you're interested, you can take a look at it.
I will not go through all these difficult to read figures at the moment, but you can take a look.
But essentially the key take away is they're doing single instruction operating on multiple data
elements and the core is to X-ray, multiply and accumulate operations that are at the core of
machine learning matrix multiplication.
We're going to get back to that later on.
Any questions Now?
I'll start the GPU part with that backdrop, OK, Probably using GPUs.
How many people here have used GPUs?
Programmed GPUs, not program.
Not that many.
OK, you'll probably used it even not without knowing it in your laptop.
That doesn't count I guess.
If you talk with a ChatGPT or some sort of LLM, you're probably using it without knowing it and even
paying for it, making a lot of money for NVIDIA these days.
It's good to look for alternative models, but GPUs have been successful because they do some things
really well.
And these are some examples over here.
And it's also good to consider that we're going to talk about the processing side of things, but
there is also a networking side of GPUs, which is you need to connect many GPUs to build like train
very large models.
And for that you really need very fast communication across different machines.
And there's been a lot of innovation in the GPU space on how to design the interconnects between
different GPUs.
So that you can communicate values very fast between the GPUs.
And that's what this bottom part shows, which I'll not get into.
But if you're interested, you can take our computer architecture course where we cover interconnects
in a lot more detail.
OK.
And one of the reasons they've been successful is AI models have been growing exponentially.
And these are some of the interconnect architectures over many years.
So people have been optimising how GPUs are interconnected to each other.
For example, in this particular case, these are the, the, the small white, small white squares are
the GPUs.
And this is, there's a router network over here that connects this set of GPUs to this set of GPUs
so that they can communicate and exchange information much more easily with each each other.
OK.
But based on what we have discussed, GPUs are essentially SIMD engines underneath the instruction
pipeline that we have in a GPU operates like a SIMD pipeline, very similar to an array processor,
but it's really a combination of array and vector as we will see.
However, the major difference and I believe the major thing that has made them very successful is
their programming model.
Programming is not done like a vector processor using SIMD instructions.
It's time using threads, a much more familiar programming model for people who program CPUs, right?
When you write ACPU program, you have a single thread.
If you want to parallelise it, you have multiple threads.
And essentially in GPUs you can do the same thing.
Of course, you may not be successful in terms of getting high performance if you do the exact same
thing.
You need to exploit the SIMD parallelism that's there, which is really single instruction, multiple
data, which means that you need to construct your threads such that they operate, They do the same
thing, but they operate on different data elements.
So that's the key idea basically.
So let's go back to this parallelizable code example that I showed you earlier.
But before that, I would like to distinguish between two things.
One is the programming model, this is software, what the software programmer gets exposed to.
And the other is the underlying execution model, which is the hardware, what the hardware really
supports.
And here it's actually a fascinating area because you can mix and match anything, but sometimes
mixing and matching anything is not a good idea because the programming model may not match the how
the hardware executes things and vice versa.
Potentially in GPUs, there's a programming model that very nicely matches the execution model.
OK, but let's cover this concept a little bit more because this is bigger than the GPUs also.
So a programming model, as I said, refers to how the programmer expresses the code.
For example, you see in sequential programming models, one moment we've seen data parallel SIMD
programming models.
In the last lecture, we've seen data flow programming models, either graphical or non graphical.
We've seen partially not as much, but MIMD programming models, if you've done multi threaded
programming, if you've done parallel programming, and probably a lot of you have done, how many
people have done multi threaded programming on CPUs here?
Pretty much all of you basically.
That's MIMD, multiple instruction streams operating on different data elements, right?
There is a special version of MIMD which is SPMD, which is a programming model that GPUs are going
to use.
We'll introduce that in a little bit.
Essentially the idea is you have multiple threads, but they're doing exactly the same thing on
different data elements.
That single program, multiple data, OK execution model refers to how the hardware executes the code
underneath.
And we've seen a lot of execution models actually in this class so far.
Pipelining for example, is an execution model out of order execution, vector processing, array
processing, data flow processing, right, multi processing, multi thread processing.
These are all execution fine grain.
Multi threading is an execution model also right?
And GPUs actually will use part of that execution model also.
So essentially execution model doesn't need to match the programming models requirements, but they
could be very different.
For example, we've seen this and it's been very successful.
You have a Von Neumann programming model which doesn't expose a lot of parallelism.
But if you implement it on a restricted data flow engine, which is called out of order execution or
dynamic scheduling processors, which we've covered, you can actually extract a lot of parallelism.
These are complete different things.
Data flow is a much better fit as we've discussed, for example, potentially for an auto world
execution machine, because fundamentally the architecture is data flow.
But nobody programs these things using a data flow model, right?
Why?
Because programming model is a lot easier if it's single instruction, single data, right, If it's
sequential.
And that's been the success of auto world execution CPUs.
There's a nice programming model and underlying hardware execution model doesn't quite match it.
Initially it matched it actually, but over time it got extended such that it exploits a lot of
parallelism and this has been very successful in GPUs.
We will see that there's a nice programming model also, and the hardware actually.
It matches it really nicely, but as a result it's not going to be as general purpose, OK.
And that's going to be the SPMD single program multiple data model implemented by a SIMD processor.
And there's a lot of research in GPUs to make it essentially a first class general purpose computing
unit.
In fact, when I was at CMU Carnegie Mellon, one of the big proposals that we wrote to the National
Science Foundation, which used to have found a lot of research at the time, was on enabling GPUs as
first class computing engines.
And we did a lot of research to enable the GPUs to execute arbitrary pieces of code.
I'm not going to talk about these.
There's a lot of possibilities over there, and there's more research that's going on in this area
right now.
But the hardware execution model in GPUs is SIMD, which limits what you can do, but it matches the
SPMD model really well.
OK, so let's go through this code example.
This is the same code example that you have seen, and the question now is more general.
How can you exploit the parallelism that is present in this code example?
And there's a lot of parallelism here, assuming I is very large.
And remember, in graphics, I is very large.
OK, so this is the scalar sequential code.
Every iteration comes after the previous iteration and we're going to look at 3 programming options
to exploit instruction level parallelism that's present in the sequential code.
1 is going to be sequential, the other is going to be data parallel SIMD, and the other is going to
be multi threaded MIMD and we're going to specialized it with SPMD also.
OK, sequential, you're very familiar with this is the sequential code you write.
It's very easy to write.
It can be executed on many things.
The pipeline processor, an out of order execution processor, which finds the independent
instructions and executes them when they're ready, right?
With a large window, for example, if that loads, stalls, for example, you can execute some other
iteration because you have a window, you can bring in instructions.
And if you think about it, what out of order execution does is it takes these different iterations
that are independent of each other and executes them in parallel in multiple functional units.
It doesn't explicitly, it's not aware of these iterations, of course, right, because you're writing
single threaded code.
But it's really unrolls these iterations dynamically if you think about it.
So if your window sizes for example 100 and if you have 4 instructions, unfortunately we're not
showing the branches over here, forget about the branches, let's say 5 instructions per iteration,
then you can have 20 iterations inside the machine right now.
You can exploit the parallelism across those 20 iterations.
That's how an out of order execution machine accelerates sequential code and we've seen this in in
past lectures.
You can also add superscalar or VLIW execution.
Usually out of order executions combined with superscalar.
And VLIW has a different philosophy as we have discussed.
And they also exploit instruction level parallelism by fetching and executing multiple instructions
per cycle.
And VLIW on top of that gives a lot of opportunity and freedom to the compiler so that the compiler
can do compile time reordering of the code so that it can exploit parallelism, right?
And the compiler can do a really great job in this particular case because every iteration is
independent of each other, right?
So this is also a very good fit for VLIW if you think about it.
OK, let's take a look at data parallel SIMD, which we discussed last time.
Single instruction, multiple data.
Clearly we realise that each instruct, each iteration is independent of every other iteration.
In this particular case, that's what it means to be fully vectorizable.
So what we can do is we can take iterations and put them next to each other pictorially.
And you can do this either as a programmer or as a compiler and program.
Actually, hardware can do this also, but we're not talking about that with the SIMD programming
model.
But programmer or compiler generates a SIMD instruction to execute the same instruction from all
iterations across different data.
All iterations is the ideal case.
You're limited by the vector length, of course, in a real machine.
But if your iteration count is smaller than your vector length, then all the iterations is correct.
OK, so basically the compiler or the programmer takes the same instruction from different iterations
and forms a vector instruction, right?
And that's our vector load.
You basically take vector loads, load A into vector register 1, and you also create another vector
load for loading B into vector register two.
Another vector instruction vector adds V1 plus V2.
Store the result in V3 and then a vector store.
Sounds good, right?
You've seen this also, we've actually gone through a code.
Examples.
One big advantage over here is you also eliminate branches.
So that's one upside over here, we couldn't eliminate branches in the previous case, but here we
eliminate the branches, which is nice.
And you've seen that last week, OK, So this is best executed by ASIMD processor because SIMD
processor essentially is built such that the hardware execution units do the same operation except
on different data elements, right?
Either in time or space.
OK, so a data parallel programming model is nice for SIMD processors.
You could also execute this in out of order execution processor, right?
You just need to convert those vector instructions to scalar instructions like or some sort of micro
operations.
Basically would waste a lot of the beauty of SIMD if you if you do that right.
I wouldn't recommend doing that unless you have to do it for binary compatibility reasons.
Then you don't have anything else to execute this on.
So that's the mismatch between programming model and hardware execution model if you think about it.
OK, now let's take a look at the multi threaded version of this.
So this is scalar sequential code.
Again the same example multi thread execution model.
Programmer or compiler realises again each iteration is independent and essentially assigns each
iteration to a different thread.
It does not form vector instructions across iterations.
Each thread, basically a programmer or compiler, generates a thread to execute each iteration.
Each thread does exactly the same thing, but on different data elements.
That's the idea over here.
We're accomplishing the same thing, but we're not changing the instructions here.
The instructions are still scalar.
Load, load, add, store and we have N number of scalar threads.
Makes sense, right?
Clearly you program things like this with multi threading.
This can be executed on a mimd machine where you have multiple CPUs.
Each can be actually very wimpy CPUs.
Remember the 1000 chickens?
So each each CPU can be something that doesn't even have pipelining for example, right?
Assuming the code, the iterations are very simple and you have a lot of parallelism in the CPU.
Multiple instruction multiplate the multi threaded processor multiprocessor.
This particular model, because of how the loop is, is also called single program multiple data.
Because the program or the thread is the same, right?
Except different.
Except the threads do the same thing on different data, right?
So the model itself is not SIMD anymore because we don't.
We didn't create instructions that operate on multiple pieces of data.
We created threads that do the same thing on different pieces of data.
So that's the realisation and this is what has made GP us very successful because it's a lot easier
to reason about, it's a lot easier to write.
You don't need to extract vector instructions, you don't need to deal with vector lengths, for
example, as we will see.
So this can be executed on a SMDSMD machine.
You could actually have ACD machine, a more rigid machine, you could take these and actually
generate these vector instructions dynamically.
Again, I wouldn't do that if you have a GPU, but you could do it.
It can also be executed on a single instruction, multiple thread machine.
This is actually Nvidia's terminology, but it's been pretty successful.
Essentially, you have single instructions, multiple threads, scalar threads that are doing the same
thing on different operations.
So this will become more clear.
So GPU is essentially ACD machine.
NVIDIA calls the SIMT machine because there's a slight difference and the difference is really you
don't program using SIMD instructions.
It's kind of not clean in the sense that it mixes up the programming model and the execution model a
little bit.
That's why I think in a, from a, from an execution model hardware perspective, this is SIMD machine.
But of course it needs to have some notion of threads.
So they're also right.
They're not completely wrong in this terminology.
OK, basically, except it's not programmed using SIMD instructions.
It is programmed using threads, which is the SPMD programming model which essentially everybody's
familiar with.
Each thread executes the same code, but operates on a different piece of data.
We set this.
Each thread has its own context.
This is essentially a thread.
Basically every thread in a multi threaded program has its context, meaning its registers, its
memory, and they may share memory.
Of course, in a shared memory context.
They can be treated independently, they can be restarted independently, they can be executed
independently, they could be scheduled or unscheduled independently of each other.
So this sort of flexibility doesn't exist in a vector instruction.
Right here you may have 64,000 threads and each of them you can decide to schedule or deschedule
right and.
You're going to see that existing GPUs do that.
When one thread stalls, they bring in some other thread so they can tolerate the latency of the
stalling, and stalling is usually due to memory.
But we'll also see some other reasons.
OK, now I'm going to describe some more terminology.
It's actually not bad terminology, but different companies use different terms.
And media uses warp, AMD uses wavefront.
AMD used to be ATI, which is also a graphics company.
Essentially, a set of threads executing the same instruction are dynamically grouped into a warp or
wavefront by the hardware.
This is not a programming construct.
As we will also see again, this is really how the hardware treats these threads that are at the same
program counter.
So the hardware, because it's a thread, it's a sequential scalar thread.
There's a program counter, and each program counter belong.
Each thread has a program counter, and hardware figures out which threads are at the same program
counter and groups them together.
Because if you're at the same program counter, you're executing the same instruction, right?
Good to think about that.
OK, so basically a warp is essentially A SIMD operation formed by hardware, right?
And that's what GPUs are very good at doing.
GPUs don't require the programmer or the compiler to do this.
They do it in hardware in a very, let's say high level sense.
It's somewhat similar to how we do single threaded programming on out of order execution, on, on, on
on an out of order execution machine.
An out of order execution machine kind of figures out which instructions can be executed
independently.
Right here we have multiple multi threaded programming and the GPU figures out which instructions
can be combined together because they're at the same program counter.
So the hard work is done by the hardware, no pun intended.
Hard and hard soft work is left to the software.
I like that.
OK anyway, so basically warp is a set of threads that execute the same instruction that the same PC.
So for example this is warp 0 at PCX and X is the program counter of the load.
This is warp 0 at PCX plus one right?
Basically the way you execute multiple threads is you go through the same warp, except every warp
increments its program counter, right?
Different scalar threads that are at the same program counter keep incrementing their program
counters, right?
This is warp 0 at PCX +2, this is warp 0 at PCX +3.
And at some point the thread is done OK.
This means that also you may have millions of warps, right?
If for example, your image is 32,000,000 pixels, for example, and each thread has 32 instructions,
you have 1,000,000 threads over here, right?
And if each warp is, let's say, I don't know, let's say 100 instructions at the same time, then
that's 1,000,000 / 100, right?
10,000, I guess you can have 10,000 threads based 10,000 warps.
OK, OK, basically I think I've given you the key idea.
We're going to now look at the benefits of this.
Graphics processing units are SIMD, not exposed to the programmer, and we're looking at the core,
these are called shader cores, essentially core of the graphics of processing units, basically the
computation core.
They're also graphics units have been around since let's say late 1980s.
They were put to do image processing, display processing, and over time more intensive graphics
tasks.
So there's a lot of specialised units also like the texture unit, we're not going to cover those.
More recently there are ray tracing units that are very specialised for graphics computations.
This is the more general purpose part of the graphics unit that has really enabled computations like
machine learning, training and inference.
So we're not learning everything about graphics processing units.
Keep that in mind, but we cannot cover everything about them.
Also, some of it you need to read.
OK, let's take a look at the SIMD and SIMD execution model a little bit more.
SIMD is a single sequential instruction stream of SIMD.
Essentially in the SIMD model, you have a single sequential instruction stream of SIMD instructions,
right?
Each instruction specifies multiple data inputs.
In a sense.
There is no notion of a threat.
So we've seen this for example, you have that particular example, you have two vector loads, one
vector add 1 vector store and you need to specify a vector length, right?
And that needs to be done.
Somebody needs to specify the vector length where simply you have multiple instruction streams of
scalar instructions and threads are dynamically grouped into warps.
If I had to summarize it, you don't have VS anymore.
Instructions are exactly the same as a sequential ISA like.
Von Neumann ISA load, load, add, store and you basically specify the number of threads.
That's the high level perspective, right?
We replaced vector length with number of threads and also vector instructions are gone.
So what are the advantages of this?
We're going to examine two major advantages.
There are a bunch of other ones, but those are secondary in my view.
One major advantages, you can treat each thread separately, meaning you can execute each thread
independently on any type of scalar pipeline, including an auto order pipeline potentially if you
want, and this leads to MIMD processing.
You can also group threads into warps flexibly because these are not programming constructs, right?
A vector length is a programming construct, A vector load is a programming construct, but a warp is
not a programming construct.
Hardware dynamically figures out which threads are truly executing the same instruction and can
dynamically group them together and maximise the benefits of SIMD processing.
This is something a compiler cannot do.
For example, if you have irregularity in your code, for whatever reason, the compiler may not be
able to form vector instructions and it can give up, whereas all the hardware here needs to do is
figure out which threads are executing in the same program counter.
So in a sense, it's relatively general purpose.
OK, let's start with the first one.
And all of this actually affects the programming ease, right?
It makes it easier to program these machines.
OK, so let's take a look at these warps and treating them separately.
These are threads, so you can actually do a fine grain multi threading.
While one thread is executing, 1 warp is executing 1 instruction, another warp can be executing
another instruction.
Another warp can be executing another instruction.
Other warp can be executing another instruction.
These warps are completely independent of each other, so your pipeline can be very simple.
And that's essentially how GPUs make their pipeline simple.
For example, let's assume a warp consists of 32 threads.
If you have 32,000 iterations and one iteration per thread, you have 1000 warps, right?
Warps can be interleaved on the same pipeline using fine grained multi threading.
This is a concept that we've seen.
You have different threads and each stage in the pipeline is executing a different an instruction
from a different thread, right?
And this has enabled us to get rid of branch prediction.
For example, this has enabled us to get rid of data dependency checking.
So it's a beautiful pipeline.
And we said when we covered fine grained multi threading that for this to be successful you need to
have a lot of parallelism in terms of number of threads.
Now the good news is in graphics there's a lot of parallels, right?
That's why fine grained multi threading has been very successful in the graphics domain.
OK, so let's take a look at this example, the same code again.
This is warp 0 at PCX, which is its load.
And then you can bring in warp one at PCX and look at the iterations.
So you can basically identify which iteration you're executing based on everything that I've written
over here, right?
These are warp 0 at PCX is executing iteration 0 through 31 because you have 32 loads that
particular load.
If you if I tell you I have warp one at PCX, then it has to start from the 32nd iteration, right?
So that warp belongs to 32nd through a 63rd iteration.
And you can do this arbitrarily.
For example, if I tell you warp 20 at PCX +2, which is that add instruction, this is iteration #20 *
32 and the next one is iteration times #20 * 32 + 1 and the last one is 20 * 32 + 31, right?
Those are the warps.
Those are the iterations that are being executed by warp 20 at that particular program counter.
And you know that it's at OK, so this is the fine grain multi threading.
Again, I'm not showing you the hardware but pictorially because all threads are independent of each
other, warps can be executed seamlessly in fine grained multi threaded pipeline.
So for example when warp 0 is at PCX plus three in the pipeline, it's doing some store.
For example, warp one at PCX +2 can be executing at right and warp 2 at PCX plus 2X plus one can be
executing this load and warp 3 at PCX can be executing this load.
They could be executed on different parts of the machine, assuming you have enough functional units
of course, right?
That's the idea.
Basically the key is providing enough functional units so that you can actually have this
parallelism exploited in this fine grained multi threaded manner.
So hopefully that's clear.
Basically what we did was we did the same thing as fine grained multi threading, except in fine
grained multi threading earlier we just have a single instruction stream right?
Now we don't have a single instruction stream.
We have many instruction streams, except they're doing the same thing.
And we Group A particular set of threads, 32 threads into a warp and we fine grain multi thread.
Those warps right in to be, to be like more, let's say, correct.
This is really fine grain multi warping in a sense, right?
You're really doing this warping thing.
OK, so you you remember the fine grain multi threading basic idea.
Of course this comes at a cost.
You need to actually have support for threads and GPUs have a lot of context as we will see later
on.
So we will need program counter support, we will need register files for different threads.
So GPUs will actually dedicate a lot of their area to support thousands and thousands and thousands
of threads, OK.
If you want to brush up your memory on fine grain multi threading, we have lectures as you know.
OK, let me see.
Maybe that's a good time to take a break.
Let's take a break.
But I will start earlier so that I want I can cover everything.
I may leave you early today.
Let's take a break until 1512 and then we'll continue.
And if you have questions let me know.
OK, before going forward there was a very good multiple good comments.
One is remember that these warps are formed dynamically for instructions or threads that are at the
same program counter.
Once you group multiple threads into a warp, you execute them on ASIMD engine, meaning it has the
characteristics of SIMD execution.
If one of the threads stalls, the other is also stalls because these this group of threads called
the warp are treated as a single entity, just like a vector instruction.
Remember this from the SIMD lecture, we call this lock step execution, right?
You have lock step characteristic and that exists over here also in a sense it has.
It also exists in BLIW for example.
But that limits the flexibility that you have the grouping of instructions.
Of grouping of the same program counter into multiple warps enables you to reduce some of the
control overheads.
For example, if you have a single thread executing on a single pipeline, not ACD pipeline, where you
group things you need to decode, you need to fetch decode that instruction.
Here you're grouping the same instruction from different threads together, so you only need to fetch
and decode once for all threads in the warp.
It's very similar to SIMD in that sense, right?
But we have different threads, so grouping things into warps.
Grouping instruction into warps enables you to really amortise the control overheads.
So you don't need to have 32 fetch and decode units, you have only one fetch and decode unit.
And because you grouped many warps, many threads into a warp 32, for example, it could be 1024, we
will see those numbers later on.
Then you you unleash a lot of parallelism by fetching and decoding a single instruction.
So that's a huge benefit of GPUs over CPUs.
That control overhead is reduced.
The downside is flexibility is also reduced, Right?
OK, OK, now let's go into a little bit more of this.
I'm going to say essentially similar things, but we're going to build up to some interesting
concepts.
So these are from the NVIDIA Tesla paper that I recommended from 2008.
But a set of threads that execute the same instruction are called warp.
These are on different data elements.
NVIDIA calls the SIMT.
Essentially, the reason it's called warp is all threads run the same code.
And in English, a warp refers to like in woven fabric, like like this cloth, for example.
A warp is essentially the threads that run length 5 and lengthwise.
And woven fabric, if you think about it, these are doing exactly the same thing.
I don't have it, unfortunately.
I should have worn something like that.
But essentially the threads are going down like that, and they're doing essentially the same thing
as they go down.
Anyway, that's where the analogy ends.
Maybe AMD calls us wavefronts, but they do essentially the same thing.
Wavefront is equal to warp, so this is a good representation of a warp.
It's dynamically formed if there's a.
So there needs to be some hardware to detect which threads are at the same program counter.
We're going to look at it a little bit more detail, but there's some complexity that's added to
hardware.
If threads are at the same program counter, they're grouped together, but they're also some other
things that you need to consider when grouping threads together, like which registers they're
accessing, for example, which iterations they're from.
Basically, what is their thread ID basically.
In other words, you cannot take a thread ID that's let's say whose modulus over the warp warps per
thread is 0 and put them together with another thread ID whose modules is 0 because they need to
access the same register file and the register files partitioned.
So you cannot basically put together threads that need to go to the same lane, right?
So this grouping needs to be done much more carefully.
And if you're wrong, basically your hardware will be wrong.
You should not be wrong.
OK, so essentially you have these different warps and they're there.
There's a scheduler over here, which is this picture over here that keeps, you can call it also
thread warps.
Essentially, normally people drop the thread and they called warps that that keep a lot of warps
that are ready to be scheduled.
And when the pipeline is empty, these warps go into the pipeline.
Your pipeline may be, let's say.
6 stages, 10 stages, but you may actually have thousands of warts outstanding waiting to be
scheduled on that pipeline.
10 stages, but the width can be 32, for example, right?
So you may be executing 32 * 10 things at the same time.
OK, so this is the higher level view of the GPU.
As I said, we're looking at the what is called the shader core.
This is the more most general purpose part of the GPU.
Clearly memory is important.
We're going to talk a lot about that.
There's an older picture.
We're at GDDR 7 these days.
That's a graphics DDR, which is specifically designed for high bandwidth.
Today, HPM is even higher bandwidth, high bandwidth memory.
We're going to talk about that in memory lectures later on.
But essentially these cores need to be fed with very good memory subsystem.
If you look at the core you have, these are the.
This is a representation of a warp.
You have program counter and you have some number of threads that is part of a warp that's a 32.
You also have something called a mask.
This means that basically this is a mask of which threads are active in this program counter.
Because of branching, the threads that are part of the same program counter may actually go
different paths, and we'll see that some threads become inactive if they are not supposed to
execute this path of the branch, and some threads become active if they are supposed to execute
that path on the branch.
So this is called the active mask in GPUs.
It basically identifies which warps which threads in the warp is supposed to execute that program
counter.
That's it basically.
Normally if there's no branching, all the active mask is all full of ones, meaning all threads are
supposed to execute that program.
Counter branching complicates things as we will see in a little bit.
But this is no different from vector masking.
Actually it's as you have seen in the last lecture.
In SIMD lecture we talked about masking V mask.
For example, GPUs do that without requiring vector mask registers.
They have these masks that are associated with each warp.
OK, So you, you fetch the instruction from the I cache instruction cache and then there is a single
decode unit.
It's unfortunately not nice over here in this picture.
It's actually a very small unit, I would say.
And then that decode unit distributes the same operation to different parts of the pipeline,
different register files essentially.
So if you look at the pipeline, they're all scalar.
They're actually independent of each other, but they're used together because there is only a single
fetch and single decode unit feeding many processing elements, right?
Essentially it's SIMD, except we don't use SIMD instructions.
OK, so we've also seen this.
I'll go through this relatively quickly, but I'll mention a couple of things over here.
We've already discussed a lot of these.
So you have one instruction per thread in the pipeline at a time.
So there's no need for hardware interlocking.
That's the benefit of fine grained multi threading.
There's no need for branch prediction over here.
There's no need for data dependency checking the pipeline.
The scalar pipeline is really, really simple and we discussed that we interleave warp execution to
hide latencies.
So register values of all threads stay in the register file, which is partitioned as you can see
over here.
And fine grain multi threading enabled as a very simple pipeline and long latency tolerance.
Imagine millions of threads operating on the same large image or video, for example.
I'll mention one thing over here that's going to be important later on.
Today's memory latencies are not 11 cycles like Cray one.
They're like on the order of hundreds of cycles.
For example, Microsoft Xbox which is CPU, but they did actually add a lot of graphics units later
on.
The memory access latency was 650 cycles, clock cycles, and to tolerate that latency they add a lot
of multi threading and fine grain.
Multi threading enables us also.
Basically, if you get a cache miss, for example, when you're accessing the cache, you have a load
instruction.
Then what the scheduler or the pipeline does is it takes out the warp.
It sends the request to memory, of course, to get the data, but it takes out the warp and puts them
in a special queue, a queue of or a structure that contains the warps that are accessing the memory
hierarchy.
Currently they wait there until the associated memory request comes back and wakes them up.
Makes sense, right?
This is scheduling that you do in hardware so that you can tolerate the memory latency.
You need to remove that warp so that doesn't block the pipeline for everyone else, right?
Very similar to auto war execution, except it's done in a much more regular manner.
So this queue can be pretty large also.
So there are two queues over here.
There are warps that are available for scheduling currently they're ready, they can go.
They feed the pipeline, the fetch engine and there there the other queue is there.
Warps that are waiting for memory accesses essentially, and those are where the scheduling points
come, because when the data comes back for all the threads in the warp, this is where data mapping
will be important. If different threads are not accessing sequential parts of memory, you may need
to access very different parts of memory, and as a result you may need to wait for a long time in
that warp, right.
We'll get back to that also, but you've seen scatter gather operations, for example in SIMD. You can
do the same things in G in GP US and they, if they're, if they're irregular, if you're accessing,
for example, random places in memory, because you're gathering data from random places, because
you're accessing a very sparse matrix, for example, then those warps would be waiting in that queue
for a long time because they need to issue a lot of memory requests. This is where things get a
little bit complicated and sometimes nasty.
Because a single warp. Assume that the warp is 32 threads. If if the accesses are irregular, meaning
each of them computes an address that has nothing to do with the other addresses, you'll probably
need to issue 32 memory requests. And you need to wait for all of those 32 memory requests to come
back so that you can schedule back that warp into the pipeline OK and after warps get scheduled.
They write back, they finish their instruction, they go back to the ready warp queue essentially. So
that's how scheduling happens in a GPU. That's all hardware based scheduling. OK, so you've seen
this picture. We're going to go through the same thing, except we're going to look at warps right
now. This is a vector add instruction that we've seen in SIMD and we exploited parallelism in space
as well as time essentially. If you look at a 32 thread warp executing.
This instruction, this instruction is not a vector instruction anymore. It's essentially A scalar
instruction where the arrays are indexed by the thread ID, right? That's the beauty of the
programming model that we have. You can execute it using a single scalar unit or you can execute it
using multiple scalar units. And essentially it's the same over here, right? The slide didn't
change except how we programmed it changed.
Makes sense, right? So this clearly demonstrates that an existing GPU is ASIMD unit. The hardware
did not change right ASIMD machine OK, So similarly to the SIMD machines we parti remember in that
case we partitioned the vector registers. A particular elements are in particular register
partitions. So for example, this partition register file component as elements 048, this one is
159...
In GPUs we essentially have the same thing. I keep going back and forth over here, but instead of
having elements zero, you have registers for thread ID 048. For example, on this partition,
register for thread ID is 159 on the other partition, etcetera. So not much has changed as you can
see. But this is going to limit our flexibility in how we group together threads. Also, for
example, if you have threads that.
Are at the same program counter, but their IDs are 048. You cannot group them together because they
need to access the same link, right? OK, so vector instruction level parallelism. I don't want to
harp on this too much essentially, but now you have warp instruction level parallelism. A warp may
be executing a load, unleashing 32 loads. Another warp may be unleashing 32 multiplies, another
warp 32 ads.
Essentially, different warps can be enabling a lot of operations at the same time. And remember, we
have a lot of warps. OK, let's talk about memory access a little bit. So if you want to have this
very regular, especially for example, if you have, if you're going through an array, that's the
best case for a GPU because the same instruction, different threads, different threads uses the
thread ID to index and access different data elements.
For example, warp 0 in this particular case has four threads. It's accessing 4 data elements and you
need to partition your data elements nicely. If you have a single array, it's natural of course
0123.
So warp 0 accesses data element 0, warp 1 access data element, basically warp 0 access data element
0123 in this particular case. And we will see later that those sequential accesses are actually
relatively fast from memory, because as we will see again in future lectures about memory, they
could be nicely packed into the cache. Even if they're not in the cache, they could be nicely
packed into the same bank.
OK, but basically the take away is if you're partitioning your data nicely, you can access it at
high throughput without hopefully stalling as much.
So for maximum performance, memory should provide enough bandwidth and that's why GPUs require much
higher bandwidth memories.
This means that elements per cycle throughput should match computation unit throughput, right?
Ideally, right, Because if your computation unit throughput is much higher than the elements per
cycle that you can provide to those computation units, you'll have to stall in the end.
Now that's the case actually today.
So we stall a lot.
OK, so warps are not exposed to programmers, so this should be clear by now, but I'm going to say
this again.
You have CPU threads and GPU kernels.
And normally if you have sequential code or modestly parallel sections, it it's best to execute them
on CPUs.
That's why heterogeneous computing is very useful.
You have a heterogeneous CPU and GPU and you have the sequential and or mostly modestly parallel
sections execute on ACPU that's powerful on those.
Whereas massively parallel sections are a much better fit for GPU and the way programmer programs.
I will very briefly go into the programming at a higher level.
The GPU programmer uses blocks and that's what's visible to the programmer.
You have some serial code and then you have some parallel kernel in GPU terminology.
Again, that's sent to the device because initially GPUs were devices that are attached to CPUs.
There were more accelerators.
They're becoming more general purpose now, and this is how a programmer specifies you have a kernel,
you have number of blocks and number of threads and some arguments to it, and then you have serial
code that's executed on the host and then you do another parallel kernel.
Basically, that's how things go if you have some heterogeneous execution.
And if you look at the sample, a sample GPU code, it's relatively simple to write.
Of course, this is a bit simplified, but this was our picture.
This was our function, right that I showed you earlier, written in a slightly different way with
IIS, for whatever reason, I don't know, I'd prefer, II guess some people prefer IIS.
You could go multiply IS and CUDA codes.
CUDA is a special programming model that NVIDIA owns, let's say, and that's one of the reasons why
they're very successful also because they own it.
Essentially, the code is the same.
If you look over here, you index the arrays using thread IDs and you do the computation and write
the results into the destination area using thread ID.
The only difference is the programmer needs to deal with partitioning of the data across blocks.
So this is imagine you, you're partitioning a big image, you're partitioning into the blocks and
then threads.
That's what you need to do.
There's some more bells and whistles, but if you want to do GPU programming, you can learn that
relatively easily.
So this is another example sampled CPU program that does something a little bit more complicated,
and this is the GPU program that corresponds to it.
You don't need to understand everything over here, but the key take away is the kernel is
essentially the same, right?
Slightly rewritten so that you can compute thread IDs and block IDs appropriately.
But there's no notion of warp in the end over here.
This is your program, this is your thread.
There are many of them, and the data is partitioned by the programmer.
Warps are formed all dynamically.
OK, we have Electron GPU programming.
I guess we used to have it sometimes, but we don't have enough material to cover.
So if you're interested, you can look at this lecture on GPU programming.
We also have a course actually, that we used to give on GPU programming and more generally
heterogeneous systems.
These materials are all online.
A lot of people in the industry actually still use it and ask us why we don't continue this.
We just don't have enough bandwidth.
It's like the memory bandwidth, you know, you cannot basically pump enough data out, but there's
demand basically for this sort of thing because a lot of people are actually doing this sort of
programming.
OK, so let's take a look at how you get from blocks to warps a little bit.
A GPU core is a SMD pipeline.
NVIDIA calls it streaming processor.
There are many such streaming processors, SMD processors.
NVIDIA calls it streaming multiprocessor.
I don't necessarily like this terminology.
It's called streaming course.
You can look it up, we can learn more.
But essentially it looks like this.
There are many streaming processors that are essentially SIMD pipelines and this is 1 streaming
multi processor.
And there are many of these streaming multiprocessors in AGPU.
We will see this more later, but you can see there's a warp scheduler, dispatch unit, register file,
a single very simple instruction, fetch engine, big scheduler, and most of the areas dedicated to
hopefully doing computation except for the memory hierarchy that we will discuss later on.
So you have the blocks that are specified by the.
Programmer, they're divided into warps, and warps are essentially the SIMD or SIMD unit.
It could be 32 threads.
And this is what they kind of look like, right?
These are block zeros, warps, for example.
These are block ones, warps, and these are block twos, warps, and they basically can get mapped to
different streaming multiprocessors.
OK, so mapping is another issue that we're not going to discuss in this course, but there's a lot of
work on how to map different blocks and different warps to different streaming processors to
maximise memory bandwidth usually, but we're not going to talk about that.
OK, let me start wrapping up a little bit the benefits and then we're going to talk about some other
benefits.
So traditional SIMD contains a single thread, right?
You have sequential instruction execution, lockstep operations on a SIMD instruction, programming
model SIMD, no extra threads.
Software needs to know the vector length.
Basic software needs to emit vector instructions.
ISA contains vector and SIMD instruction.
It requires an ISA change.
Also, warp based SIMD, which is essentially what we've been talking about, consists of multiple
scalar threads executing in a SIMD manner.
Same instruction executed by all threads, right?
Doesn't have to be lockstep.
For that particular warp it's lockstep, but for everything else it's not lockstep, right?
Once you group threads into a warp, it's lock step, but you can break it.
Also later on it's good to think about that each thread can be treated individually, in other words,
placed in a different warp.
So programming models essentially not SIMD software doesn't need to know the vector length, software
doesn't need to know anything.
Actually the programmer doesn't need to know vectors, they just need to think about blocks and
threads.
And this enables multi threading and flexible dynamic grouping of threads, which we will get.
Importantly, ISA is scalar.
So you can take an existing scalar core, a very wimpy one, and put it in your GPU, replicate it many
times.
It's easy design, right?
Of course you need to design everything else around it to supply the warps.
But you don't need to change the ISA, for example, right?
And we know that ISA changes are not easy to make.
OK, SIMD operations are formed dynamically.
Essentially we'll get back to the same thing.
It's SPMD programming model implemented on SIMD hardware.
I think we've already talked about SPMDI will not talk about that.
But maybe one question comes to your mind is the same procedures execute on different data elements,
but how do they synchronise?
So clearly when you divide a program into many threads, at some point they need to synchronise
potentially, unless you're really embarrassingly parallel and they never need to synchronise.
That's ideally the whole world.
But unfortunately, well, fortunately, there's a lot of synchronisation that needs to happen at some
point.
GPUs need special structures for that.
NVIDIA unfortunately calls it shared memory, for example.
There's some shared memory structure shared across different units, different streaming
multiprocessors.
That's how you do the synchronisation.
There needs to be some synchronisation operations to synchronise between different warps
essentially, or blocks anyway.
We're not going to talk about that, but you can.
You'll need to do that if you actually do GPU programming, for example, I think we've said all of
this, but maybe I will say that each program and procedure works on different data and can execute
a different control flow path at runtime.
So we're going to get to this different control flow path.
Actually, many scientific applications before GPUs were programmed this way.
So if you take a scientific program, some molecular dynamic simulation for example, there's a lot of
parallelism over there too.
You break it, you break the world of molecular dynamics into blocks, and you assign threads into it.
Every thread does the same thing.
In the past, when GPUs were not as popular or as powerful, people used to have supercomputers,
right?
They still have these supercomputers with GPUs, but essentially the programming model was the same.
You have single program or single procedure multiple data, except they were executed on many CPUs,
for example.
GPUs made this easier.
OK, we we've seen this picture.
Now I'm going to talk about the second major SIMT advantage.
Any questions?
Everybody is following enjoying GPUs, I guess.
OK, let's talk about the second advantage because this is actually very interesting.
You can group threads into warps flexibly.
In other words, you can group threads that are supposed to truly execute the same instruction.
And as a result, you can dynamically obtain and maximise benefits of SIMD processing even if your
program is not SIMD, as we as we have in GPUs.
Let's take a look at this example.
We're going to complicate things because real world is complicated, right?
You have conditional control flow instructions which made our life harder in pipelining for example.
It's going to make our life harder here also.
But we already know how to deal with them with the active masks, right?
We dealt with them with masked execution in vector process.
So we're going to do something similar over here.
Each thread can execute different control flow paths.
So each thread is supposed to execute this code.
Clearly, there are branches over here.
There's a control flow graph over here.
These are different basic blocks.
It could be some set of instructions.
Let's say the thread one is supposed to take this path.
Thread 2 is supposed to take this path because of the data values, right?
Thread 3 is supposed to take this path, and thread 4 is supposed to take this path, right?
If you group these threads into the same warp, you're basically assuming that they have the common
PC, right?
And initially they do have the common PC.
They all start from a right?
That basic block.
If that basic block is 5 instructions, they're going to execute all 5 instructions and they're all
going to be active.
But once they diverge, meaning one thread needs to go this way, another thread needs to go this way,
what you need to do is to create two different warps.
1 warp will go this way, another warp will go this way, and their active masks will be different
because different threads will need to execute that instruction.
Some threads will execute B, some some threads will execute F for example.
So basically the way you go through a control flow graph is you partition A warp into multiple warps
as you go through control flow.
Of course, if all threads go one way, you don't need to do that.
You don't need to create a separate warp because no thread is going to go this other way in a branch
thread.
So that's the idea over here.
I mean, we already said all of this over here.
You group scalar threads into warps.
This is the problem of branch divergent.
Essentially it occurs when threads inside warps branch to different execution paths.
So initially, let's assume that you have 8 threads per warp.
They're all in this program counter.
They all get to the branch, they execute the branch.
So they're still all threads are active.
Blue arrow means threads are active over here.
Now you execute the branch and you figure out that some threads need to go through path A and these
are threads 02/3 and seven.
As you can see those bits in the active mask which is at 8 elements bit vector are set saying that
at this PC this warp, these are the threads that should be executing the instructions.
Everything else goes through the functional units but the results are thrown away.
Makes sense right?
Now you create another sub warp or essentially another warp with a different active mask, which is
the complement of the active mask over here to execute path B in this particular case, right?
OK.
And eventually you need to have some mechanisms to merge these warps because you understand that
they're at the same program counter.
You don't have to have this mechanism, but having this mechanism allows you to maximise utilisation
of the pipeline, right?
So what has happened over here is these two warps are actually the same warp, but they had to
diverge, right?
And because they had to diverge, we reduce the utilisation of our pipeline, right?
Each warp could have been executing 8 instructions, but we executed 4 in each.
So our pipeline utilisation went to 50% over here and 50% over here.
It's also called SIMD utilisation and it's actually a very nice thing to ask questions about.
You will see some nice questions in the homeworks.
You can compute the SIMD utilisation of any program thrown at you if you know how AGP works please.
So ideally we don't want this, right?
Ideally we want 100% SIMD utilisation all the time, but unfortunately control flow doesn't allow you
to get that.
But what I what I've shown you over here is the same as conditional predicate or mass execution.
We call the vector mask and mass vector operations.
Except programmer doesn't deal with this, this is dealt by the hardware.
The hardware creates 2 masks that diverge.
Of course if the control flow is nested like after like something like this for example that I
showed you earlier, then you actually create more warps with different masks.
And as you go deeper in the nesting level, what happens is you reduce your SIMD utilisation.
So a control flow that diverges is not good for parallel machines like this.
It's good to think about this.
OK, so how can we fix some of this at least?
Remember, these are threads.
These are not SIMD instructions that someone dictated you should execute in lockstep.
We can actually regroup these threads by understanding which ones can be regrouped, and that's what
we're going to do.
Basically, if you have many threads that are waiting, we can find individual threads that are at the
same program counter with some search mechanism in hardware and group.
Put them together into a single warp dynamically to maximise the SIMD utilisation.
I see a thread with a warp with an active mask that has only two bits set and another another warp
with an active mask that has the remaining 6 bits set.
You can merge them so that you can have a warp with a full active mask.
Right?
That's the idea over here.
I'll show this pictorially Also.
This reduces divergent, improves SIMD utilisation and SIMD utilisation.
To define it more precisely, it's a fraction of SIMD lanes executing a useful operation.
Useful operation in this case is an active thread, right?
If you're executing a thread with the active mask bit bit mask turned off, that means you're going
to discard that result because the thread is not supposed to be executing that, right?
So your active mask needs to be set.
OK, so existing GPUs do this and more complicated things.
Let's talk about this first.
Essentially, they dynamically merge threads executing the same instruction.
In other words, at the same PC, they form new warps from warps that are waiting, and enough threads
branching to the same path enables creation of full new warps with full active masks.
For example, you have warp X and more Y.
You look at the scheduler, these are the active masks, and say, oh, I can combine these things and
get rid of one of the warps, right?
That's the idea.
It's like packing things together as long as they don't conflict in the lanes and people have
developed hardware algorithms to do this efficiently.
It's a lot of bit masking operations, by the way.
OK, so these two warps also can be grouped together, except the benefit you're going to get will not
be good.
How do you fix this?
Well, look at a bigger set of warps.
If you have a much bigger set of warps, the probability of you grouping things from that to create
full warps is going to be much higher than if you look at only a few warps, right?
That's why the scheduler in AGP has thousands of warps, OK, OK, so if you have the bigger set, now
you reduce 3 warps into two warps, and both of these two warps are more fully utilised even though
they're not perfect.
OK OK, so that's the idea of dynamic warp formation and I'll give you one more example over here.
This was path A.
Now let's assume that you have some other warp over here that also goes to path A.
You can merge these things and you can get some benefit.
In this particular case, you didn't get too much benefit.
That's why you need to look at a bigger picture.
I like this animation.
Again, I will not go through this in detail.
You can do it on your own, but here you have two warps over here and you have execution of warp X at
basic block A.
For example, you have the A over here, and this is execution of warp Y at basic block A.
This is the legend, and these are the active masks.
Initially, both warp X and worldwide have full active masks.
All four threads in the warp are active, and you can animate this and see how the execution goes in
the baseline, which doesn't dynamically merge the warps.
It looks kind of like this.
I guess I'll wait.
It's a bit slow, and we're going to save time by actually executing these things by creating a new
warp.
So this is a new warp created from scalar threads of both warp X&Y executing at basic block D, for
example.
Let's take a look at it.
So A is full.
That's good.
X&Y are both full.
Now here, by combining some things over here, you can make this warp full, but unfortunately,
because you cannot combine this one over here, right?
Because you have only four, four threads in a warp here, you can eliminate one of the warps, which
is nice.
Here you can also eliminate one of the warps.
Those are not eliminated here.
You can also eliminate one of the warps.
And in the end, even in this very simple example, you save a bunch of cycles.
That's the idea over here.
And this is very simple.
I'm showing you only two warps over here.
Imagine doing this in 10s of thousands of warps, right?
OK, so I said I said this already so I'll go through this quickly.
But hardware constraints limit flexibility of warp grouping.
You cannot move any thread flexibly to any lane because registers are partitions, and certain thread
IDs read their registers in a given partition, so it cannot conflict the thread IDs if they go to
the same partition, right?
People have some proposed mechanisms to avoid this.
This is very expensive to avoid in general.
It basically gets rid of a lot of the SIMD benefits if you try to schedule the threads to different
parts.
Either you need to expand the register file to make it a shared big register file that can be
accessed from any lane.
That's very expensive in general.
Or you need to move the registers, communicate the registers.
That's also very expensive.
In the end, the interconnection network that you need to design either to support that huge register
file or moving the data across different partitions of the registers is huge.
And as a result, it's very, very difficult to do.
OK, So analysing GPS is fun.
I will not go through this, but you can look at some of the example homeworks.
We have a lot of nice questions.
Some of them are reverse engineering questions and I like these because these really test
understanding of whether you have really understood the gist of how GPUs operate.
OK, we have some more time.
I'm going to go through a couple of other things and then discuss like how AGPU looks like today and
how it has evolved.
So we talked about pantry version.
So it's one of the reasons GPU resources are underutilized.
But as you will see in the next lectures, memory is an even bigger bottleneck and long latency
operations also destroy GPU utilisation.
I'm going to show you an example.
It's a paper that we wrote like 15 years ago together with some NVIDIA folks.
And a lot of GPS do even more complicated things than this today actually.
But let's take a look at core how, how you schedule warps.
So assume that you have some warps.
You schedule them one after another, and if they're doing the same thing, and if they're very
regular, they get to a long latency, cache miss, long latency load all at the same time, and they
all stall.
So while you're you compute and then you stall for a long time.
Imagine 600 cycle stalls.
Existing GPS actually sometimes have much longer stalls.
One way to fix this problem is to schedule differently.
As opposed to scheduling big work groups, like hundreds of them at the same time at the same PC,
group them differently.
So you group them in Group 0, they do some computation.
They get to these loads much quicker because you actually, you actually schedule from within the
smaller group first.
Not all of them are at the same PC, right?
And then you go to Group 1, which starts from an earlier PC, and they compute and they get to the
same load a little bit later.
So you overlap some latency.
And this way you can actually schedule from group 0 and Group One much earlier than before, and you
can save a lot of cycles.
If this doesn't make sense, don't worry, this is basically about how you really schedule and iterate
over groups.
So each group may have 16 or 32 warps, for example, right?
As opposed to scheduling thousands at the same program counter such that when they get to the long
latency load, they're all synchronised, finish one group much faster such that it gets ahead, and
then go to the next group that gets ahead also.
And they get to the same load instruction that misses the cache at different times such that you can
overlap the latency of computation and communication, which is memory access.
And this actually improves performance significantly, as we showed in this paper.
And this sort of scheduling mechanisms are employed in existing GPUs, even more complicated ones.
OK, another idea is to don't basically how you actually decide which warp needs to be grouped.
So we we introduced the idea of sub warping over here, which again I will not go into detail, but
you can have a mask over here.
This this is essentially the same warp but you look very carefully inside the warp so you actually
have different sub warps.
This also improves pipeline utilisation.
I will not go through that because we don't have time, but there's a lot of ideas that people have
proposed that went into how existing GPU architectures do scheduling, and a lot of them are really
related to how do you handle branch divergent, how do you handle memory, memory latency tolerance,
basically.
So I can read this paper for an early example.
Now let's go through an example GPU to see how things have evolved.
I'm going to pick NVIDIA as an example since that's more dominant today.
Although ATI actually makes nice GPUs too, they may be a bit harder to program these days.
OK, ATIAMD, this is an old GPU, but even then you will see that there is a lot of parallelism.
We're talking about 2006 or so.
This was GTX 285.
It's a consumer grade CPUGPU.
You have two.
Nvidia's language is a little bit different from what I will use.
NVIDIA says stream processors.
I said 240.
That means you have actually 30 cores and eight SIMD functional units per core.
So it kind of looks like this.
You have 8 SIMD functional units.
I'm showing multiply accumulate over here.
This is a single core with eight units.
The decode and fetch are shared across those 8 units and you have a lot of registers, 64 KB of
storage for thread context as you can see and this particular GPU grouped 32 threads such.
That they share the instruction stream.
Each group is a warp.
They redefined the warp earlier, but up to 32 warps are interleaved in a fine grain multi thread
manner and you can have up to 1024 thread context.
We're talking about 2006 doors still, and this is the GTX in full.
You have 30 cores, which amounts to more than 30,000 threads.
So that's a lot.
You can exploit a lot of parallels.
This has evolved a lot.
You can see the number of functional units per core and the gigaflops evolving a lot.
Let's take a look at what has happened.
Clearly people have added more processors like more cores and more functional units per core, right?
This is V-100 from 2015, 1617 or so, and they also added other stuff.
They basically figured out these cores are not good enough for very fast high throughput matrix
multiplication, so they added what is called tensor cores.
So this is a block diagram of V-100.
You can see that there's single precision and double precision operations are like this.
But if you use the tensor cores which are specialised for matrix multiplication, you get a lot
higher floating point throughput.
And what this looks like is very specialised architecture for.
They don't exactly discuss how the details of this NVIDIA, but it's a very specialised functional
unit for doing a lot of matrix operations concurrently.
OK, so this paper actually analysis some of what they have done and they have a theory of what they
do underneath, but you can take a look at it if you're interested.
Essentially, this paper discovers that they have 16 SIMD units per tensor core and they do 4x4
matrix multiplication.
They accumulate each cycle per tensor core again in Volta in 2017 or so.
OK, I'm going to skip that one.
So this could also be a systolic array.
I should mention that this tensor core may be a systolic array in future, I don't know or even right
now, because in the end what you're doing is matrix multiplication, right?
So you take some model and you basically multiply matrices.
So this is an HTPU which we have very briefly covered, I think in the last lecture or the previous
lecture when we talked about systolic arrays.
Essentially tensor cores can be anything, right?
Because it's done underneath, invisible to the programmer.
It could potentially be a systolic array.
And I'll let you think, what are the trade-offs between CMD and systolic arrays?
OK, we've covered systolic arrays, so you can take a look at this more so later people actually, or
MVD in this particular case, they added more cores, more functionally it's per core.
So things are getting bigger and bigger because you need to deal with more matrix multiplications,
let's say.
But they also added some more interesting things.
They added different data types because some of the data types are too expensive to support.
We're going to see that more later.
And they also added support for sparsity, and this is important.
This is the block diagram.
So if you look at the tensor core, they don't only have dense matrixes, dense matrices, but they
compress the matrix because not in machine learning especially or graph processing, when you
represent a graph or when you represent some activation functions or inputs, you don't have a lot
of the, a lot of the data zeros.
Basically, you don't need to really represent those zeros because when you multiply something with a
0, you get a 0, right?
You should not even do that computation.
And we've seen this also when we talked about SIMD execution, right?
You actually remove some of the operations.
So essentially there is a format where you compress the matrix and the compressed form matrix
encodes only non zero values and the indices of the non zero values.
So you basically have an index structure that points to which which values are at what location the
matrix and the sparse support enables the tensor core to operate to avoid operations on non zero
values.
Basically the inputs throughput at the expense of more complexity, right?
Complexity is you need to decode that matrix right now, OK.
But this actually improves throughput significantly.
And you can see that the tensor flow, tensor core throughput has improved a lot over time, OK.
So these keep improving.
As you can see more recently, not just M Media, but a lot of folks have realised that we don't want
to do computation on large data types.
32 bits, no, 16 bits, no, 8 bits, good.
4 bits, even better.
One bit, even better.
So people have figured out how to actually come up with better data types.
So I'm really introduce some of the scalable data types, for example, FP8.
So these cores are becoming more complicated because they support high precision data types.
Like 32 bits, but they also support different types of data types like brain float 16, FP 8,
etcetera and more.
Going forward, they will support even more ranges.
What this enables is again, input throughput, because if you operate on a 32 bit value, you can only
do so much.
But if you operate on a four bit value, you can use the same hardware to do eight of those
operations potentially, right?
It's good to think about that.
So you can see that FP16 throughput has, is this almost close to an exaflop?
I don't know, 1000 teraflops.
Is there an exaflop petaflop?
OK, that's good.
Yeah, it's, it's close to a petaflop.
I mean, at some point these supercomputers were trying to get the petaflops.
Now you can have it in a single GPU, as you can see.
OK, so there's more that's coming up.
I will not go into more detail, but you can read more about that.
But I will probably end with this food for thought.
We've talked about a lot of execution models, and some of these execution models are especially
developed to supply machine learning.
For example, it's good to think about which one is good for machine learning, right?
GPUs.
Clearly these shader cores were very good in SIMD, but they were not enough.
So people start adding other things on the side of the shaded course.
So if you actually do computation today, matrix multiplication today, those shader cores are not
running much.
If you're doing something right, you're actually using the tensor cores, so most of the hardware is
still not utilised very well.
It's good to think about it right.
Whereas if you look at a systolic array, you can utilise it quite well because systolic array is
much more specialised compared to a shader core like SIMD, SIMD execution.
So in terms of given the hardware, how much throughput and efficiency you're getting, If you're only
doing matrix multiplication, probably systolic arrays are much more efficient.
The problem is programming systolic arrays are harder compared to SIMD over here.
So it's good to think about these trade-offs.
There's also Fpgas, right, that we have not talked about.
I will mention this slide because this slide, I motivated this slide earlier, right where we talked
about convolutions and systolic arrays.
Convolutions, you can turn them into matrix multiplication and in turn matrix multiplication can be
executed on different types of execution units.
And the jury is still out how you actually design the best units for matrix multiplication.
I think even something as simple as matrix multiplication from my perspective, I tend to look at
many workloads that do very, very different things.
And matrix multiplication is an easy computation from my perspective because you know a lot of
things about it.
Sparse decomplicates things, of course.
Yeah, once you get sparse, now you're you need to do something smarter in coding, compression,
decompression.
OK.
I'll leave you with this, but if you're interested, you can take a look at our Heterogeneous systems
course.
And I will also mention that if you're interested in more of this, you can take our other courses
and talk to us.
I'll see you tomorrow.
Thank you.